Douglas W. Johnson Papers
Douglas W. Johnson Papers
1897-1943
Johnson, Douglas Wilson, 1878-1944.
3.0 linear ft.
American professor of geography and geology at Columbia University. Collection contains correspondence (1907-1938); clippings (1919-1940); photographs; scrapbook material (1897-1943); manuscript articles, and book reviews.
149085
Biographical History
Douglas William Johnson (1878-1944) was an American professor of geography and geology at Columbia University.
Born in Parkersburg, West Virginia on November 30, 1878, Johnson received his B.S. from the University of New Mexico in 1901 and a PhD from Columbia University in 1903. In 1912 Johnson began his teaching career at Columbia, where he remained for more than thirty years as a professor of physiography. He served as an exchange professor of applied science to French universities in 1923-1924.
As well as being an outstanding educator, Johnson was internationally recognized as an authority in his field. He was chief of the Division of Boundary Geography on the American Commission to Negotiate Peace in 1918 and 1919, served as advisor to President Woodrow Wilson on the question of Italian boundary problems, and was consulting physiographer to the Canadian Government in the Labrador Boundary Dispute in 1926.
Johnson was the author of many books and articles, and received numerous awards, commendations and honorary degrees during his lifetime. He died at the age of 65 in Sebring, Florida on February 24, 1944.
Scope and Contents of the Collection
The Douglas W. Johnson Papers consist of subject files, scrapbook material, photographs and writings. The donor's own index to correspondence is included at the beginning of the collection and the original folder title list, which does not exactly match the final arrangement but contains interesting information nonetheless.
Arrangement of the Collection
Subject files are arranged alphabetically, scrapbook material chronologically.
Subject and Genre Headings
Science and medicine; Johnson, Douglas Wilson, 1878-1944.; Earth scientists, United States.; Clippings (information artifacts); Correspondence.; Photographs.; Scientists.
Access Restrictions
The majority of our archival and manuscript collections are housed offsite and require advanced notice for retrieval. Researchers are encouraged to contact us in advance concerning the collection material they wish to access for their research.
Inventory
- Subject files
  - Adriatic and Tyrol questions, 1919-1924 (Box 1)
  - America-Yugoslav Society, 1924-1925 (Box 1)
  - American Rights League, 1915-1919; 2 folders (Box 1)
  - Biographical data (Box 1)
  - Calling cards, undated (Box 1)
  - Clippings and articles, 1919-1939 (Box 1)
  - Clippings, Sinking Coast, 1925-1940 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence
    - General, 1907-1938; 3 folders (Box 1)
    - Jefferson: The Forgotten Man, 1938 (Box 1)
    - Paysages et problemes geographique de la terre Americaine, 1927-1928 (Box 1)
  - False neutrality, 1938-1939 (Box 1)
  - Finland, 1940 (Box 1)
  - Folly of Federal Spending / Roosevelt, Franklin D., 1938-1939 (Box 1)
  - France, 1924; 2 folders (Box 1)
  - Ickes v. Gannett, 1939 (Box 1)
  - International Geographical Congress, 1928 (Box 1)
  - Miscellaneous (Box 1)
  - Miscellaneous printed material (Box 1)
  - "Muddy Thinking" address, 1933-1935 (Box 1)
  - Post-conference lectures, etc., 1919-1920 (Box 1)
  - Origin of Carolina Bays, 1942-1943 (Box 1)
  - Postcards, menus, invitations, etc. (Box 1)
  - World trip, 1929-1930 (Box 2)
- Scrapbook material
  - Volume 1 (Oversize 2)
  - General, 1897-1943; 22 folders; arranged roughly chronologically (Box 2)
  - Loose material (Oversize 2)
- Writings
  - Articles
    - Geology and strategy in the present war, 1940 (Box 2)
    - A Thanksgiving prayer of the American government, undated; typescript (Box 2)
    - War imperils America, 1940 (Box 2)
  - Books
    - Battlefields of the World War, 1921-1922; reviews (Box 2)
    - The New England-Acadian Shoreline, 1925-1927; reviews (Box 2)
    - Topography and Strategy in the War, reviews (Oversize 1)
  - Miscellaneous
    - Assorted published items (Box 2)
  - Pamphlets
    - Assault on the Supreme Court, 1937-1938 (Box 2)
    - The Next Armistice and After, 1941 (Box 2)
  - Poetry
    - Commencement Oration, 1927-1933 (Box 2)
  - Sermons
    - Untitled, undated; typescripts (Box 2)
- Photographs
  - Miscellaneous (Oversize 1)